So why does Altman seem so upset here?
그렇다면 알트먼은 여기서 왜 이렇게 화가 난 것처럼 보일까요?
After all, this interviewer
어쨌든 이 인터뷰어는
was just pointing out a basic fact that OpenAI has committed to spend over $1
OpenAI가 1조 달러가 넘는 돈을 쓰겠다고 약속했다는 기본적인 사실을 지적했을 뿐인데요,
trillion on AI infrastructure over the next eight years, despite only
향후 8년 동안 AI 인프라에, 그럼에도 불구하고 겨우
bringing in around $13 billion a year in recurring revenue,
연간 반복 매출이 약 130억 달러 수준인데도 말입니다,
less than 1% of what they're promising to spend.
약속한 지출액의 1%도 안 되는 수준입니다.
I'm no money genius- and I'm personally terrible
저는 돈의 천재가 아니고, 개인적으로는 정말
at budgeting-but that doesn't seem great.
예산을 짜는 데도 서툴지만, 그래도 그건 좋아 보이지 않습니다.
Most of the supposed growth in the American
2025년에 미국
economy in 2025 was caused by investment in AI.
경제가 성장한 것처럼 보였던 대부분은 AI 투자 때문에 생긴 것이었습니다.
That's all part of a promise being made by the industry, led by Sam Altman,
그것은 샘 알트먼이 이끄는 업계가 내놓는 약속의 일부입니다,
that once a certain level of machine learning intelligence is reached,
머신러닝 지능이 일정 수준에 도달하면,
all of our problems will be solved.
우리의 모든 문제가 해결될 것이라는 약속 말입니다.
The housing crisis,
주거 위기,
cancer,
암,
poverty,
빈곤,
climate change
기후변화,
mental health,
정신 건강,
democracy,
민주주의,
universal basic income care, a bunch of diseases, this cancer
보편적 기본소득, 돌봄, 온갖 질병들, 이 암
and that one, and heart disease
저 암, 그리고 심장병까지,
helping you try to accomplish your goals and be your best.
목표를 이루고 최고의 모습이 되도록 돕는 것까지요.
Very high quality health care.
아주 높은 수준의 의료 서비스도요.
The important new scientific discoveries
중요한 새로운 과학적 발견들,
the marginal cost of energy are going to trend rapidly toward zero.
에너지의 한계비용은 빠르게 0에 가까워질 것이라고 합니다.
The more equal world universal extreme health for everybody.
더 평등한 세상, 모두를 위한 보편적 최고 수준의 건강도요.
In exchange for all that
그 모든 것의 대가로
Altman is asking all of society to put all of our eggs-our data,
알트먼은 사회 전체가 우리의 모든 달걀, 즉 우리의 데이터
our economy, our water and resources... everything-into one basket:
우리 경제, 물과 자원... 모든 것을 한 바구니에 담으라고 요구합니다:
his. He's offering us one, massive,
바로 그의 바구니에요. 그는 우리에게 하나의 거대한,
So, should we trust Altman?
그렇다면 우리는 알트먼을 믿어야 할까요?
Should we accept his deal?
그의 거래를 받아들여야 할까요?
Is it even our choice?
그게 과연 우리의 선택이기나 할까요?
Altman isn't a technologist or scientist,
알트먼은 기술자도 과학자도 아닙니다,
He's an investor and dealmaker and really good at it... supposedly.
그는 투자자이자 협상가이고, 그 일을 아주 잘한다고들 합니다... 아마도요.
But his whole career is a series of 'just trust me, bro' moments.
하지만 그의 커리어 전체는 '그냥 믿어라, 형' 같은 순간들의 연속입니다.
So let's examine the deal
그럼 그가 제안하는 거래를
Altman is offering all of us.
우리 모두에게 무엇을 내놓고 있는지 살펴보겠습니다.
Should we believe Sam Altman's promises?
샘 알트먼의 약속을 믿어야 할까요?
And what's the cost to the rest of us if those promises
그리고 그 약속들이
turn out to be... lies?
거짓으로 드러난다면... 우리 모두가 치를 대가는 무엇일까요?
So let's go back and look closer
그럼 다시 돌아가서
at Altman's early days in the tech industry.
알트먼의 기술 업계 초기 시절을 더 자세히 보겠습니다.
Altman's first big deal was selling his first company,
알트먼의 첫 번째 큰 거래는 첫 회사를 파는 것이었습니다,
Loopt a service for locating your friends.
친구의 위치를 찾는 서비스인 Loopt였죠.
That's something that inherently needs lots of users to work, or else you're just
그런 서비스는 본질적으로 이용자가 많아야 작동하고, 아니면 그저
locating yourself.
자기 자신만 찾게 됩니다.
The operative idea seems to be ubiquity.
핵심 아이디어는 어디에나 존재하는, 즉 보편성이었던 것 같습니다.
I mean, get get it out there in more ways than you can possibly imagine.
그러니까 상상할 수 있는 것보다 훨씬 더 많은 방식으로 퍼뜨리라는 뜻입니다.
This whole time, Loopt refused to say how many users they had.
그 기간 내내 Loopt는 이용자가 몇 명인지 말하기를 거부했습니다.
Altman just insisted there were "way
알트먼은 그저 "훨씬
more users" than any other similar service.
더 많은 이용자"가 다른 비슷한 서비스들보다 있다고 주장했을 뿐입니다.
It turns out, though, that towards the end, Loopt only had 500 users.
하지만 결국 밝혀진 바에 따르면, 말기에는 Loopt의 이용자가 겨우 500명뿐이었습니다.
When Reuters reported this, Altman insisted it was "100 times"
로이터가 이를 보도하자, 알트먼은 실제로는 "100배"라고
more than that and that he'd provide evidence... He never did.
더 많고 증거를 내놓겠다고 주장했지만... 끝내 내놓지 않았습니다.
Just trust me, bro.
그냥 믿어라, 형.
Loopt sold to the Green Dot Corporation,
Loopt는 Green Dot Corporation에 매각됐고,
who shut it down immediately and never used any of the tech.
그들은 즉시 서비스를 종료했고 기술은 한 번도 쓰지 않았습니다.
Green Dot investors allege it was a dirty deal done to enrich
Green Dot의 투자자들은 이것이 부를 불리기 위해 벌어진 더러운 거래였다고 주장합니다,
Sequoia Capital, a VC firm with a stake in Loopt
Loopt에 지분을 가진 VC인 Sequoia Capital을
and two board members at Green Dot who helped approve the deal.
그리고 거래 승인에 관여한 Green Dot 이사회 멤버 두 명을 위해서였다는 것입니다.
Altman left Green Dot as soon as he was legally able,
알트먼은 법적으로 가능해지자마자 Green Dot을 떠났고,
walking away with millions for building an app that no longer existed in any form.
어떤 형태로도 더 이상 존재하지 않는 앱을 만든 대가로 수백만 달러를 챙겨 떠났습니다.
And luckily for Altman, someone saw something in him.
그리고 알트먼에게는 운 좋게도 그에게서 무엇인가를 본 사람이 있었습니다.
Peter Thiel. Thiel, who once said that Altman should be treated as
피터 틸입니다. 틸은 한때 알트먼을
"more of a messiah figure" gave Altman millions
"메시아에 더 가까운 인물"로 대해야 한다고 말했고, 알트먼에게 수백만 달러를
to start his own VC firm, Hydrazine Capital.
그의 VC 회사인 Hydrazine Capital을 시작하라고 건넸습니다.
And that's not all the capital Altman controlled.
그리고 알트먼이 통제하던 자본은 그것만이 아니었습니다.
He was also hired as president of Y Combinator, or YC,
그는 영향력 있는 벤처캐피털이자 스타트업 인큐베이터인 Y Combinator, 즉 YC의 대표로도 영입되었습니다,
an influential venture capital firm and startup incubator,
영향력 있는 벤처캐피털이자 스타트업 인큐베이터 말입니다,
where Loopt got its original funding. "I think the president of YC
Loopt가 처음 자금을 받은 곳이기도 하죠. "YC의 대표는
is sort of the unofficial leader of the startup movement."
스타트업 운동의 비공식적 리더 같은 존재"라고 생각합니다."
And Altman personally traded on that influence.
그리고 알트먼은 그 영향력을 개인적으로 활용했습니다.
The New Yorker reports that up to 75% of Hydrazine
더 뉴요커는 Hydrazine
Capital was invested in YC companies.
Capital의 최대 75%가 YC 기업들에 투자됐다고 보도했습니다.
Altman used his inside view to get a cut of
알트먼은 내부에서 보는 시각을 이용해
YC's power.
YC의 힘에서 몫을 챙긴 것입니다.
Despite Altman promising he didn't cross invest in YC companies.
알트먼은 YC 기업들에 교차 투자하지 않겠다고 약속했음에도요.
That's two big lies so far: the user base of LOOPT
지금까지 큰 거짓말이 두 가지입니다: 사용자 수가 있어야 존재할 수 있는 LOOPT의
that needed users to exist, and his investments.
사용자 기반에 대한 거짓말, 그리고 그의 투자에 대한 거짓말입니다.
In 2015, Altman leads YC into the investment you likely most know him for:
2015년, 알트먼은 YC를 이끌고 여러분이 그를 가장 잘 아는 투자로 나아갑니다:
"Sort of a semi-company, semi-nonprofit, doing AI safety research."
"일종의 반은 회사이고 반은 비영리인 형태로, AI 안전 연구를 하는 곳"입니다.
OpenAI was launched as the supposed nonprofit OpenAI Foundation with a charter
OpenAI는 소위 비영리인 OpenAI Foundation으로 출범했고, 헌장에는
with a lot of lofty goals, "a primary fiduciary duty to humanity"
수많은 고상한 목표들이 담겼습니다, "인류에 대한 1차적 신인의무"가 있고
and "avoiding enabling uses of AI or AGI
그리고 "인류에 해를 끼치거나 권력을 과도하게 집중시키는 AI 또는 AGI의
that harm humanity or unduly concentrate power," while
활용을 가능하게 하지 않기"도 포함되며, 또한
acting to "minimize conflicts of interest among our employees and stakeholders."
"직원과 이해관계자 사이의 이해상충을 최소화하기" 위해 행동한다고 했습니다.
The evidence that they'd do that? "Just trust me, bro."
그런 일을 할 거라는 증거요? "그냥 믿으라니까요."
OpenAI's primary financial
OpenAI의 주요 재정적 후원자는
backers were tech billionaires and millionaires like Altman
Altman 같은 기술 분야 억만장자와 백만장자들이었고,
himself, Peter Thiel, Reid Hoffman and Elon Musk,
Peter Thiel, Reid Hoffman, Elon Musk도 포함됐습니다.
and tech companies like Amazon Web Services and Infosys.
또 Amazon Web Services와 Infosys 같은 기술 기업들도 있었습니다.
We wanted to build this with humanity’s best interest at heart.
저희는 인류의 최선의 이익을 마음에 두고 이것을 만들고 싶었습니다.
But in exchange, OpenAI is asking for a lot...
하지만 그 대가로 OpenAI는 많은 것을 요구하고 있습니다…
Putting all of society's eggs in one basket, if you will.
말하자면 사회의 모든 계란을 한 바구니에 담는 셈입니다.
They want electricity, water, infrastructure...
그들은 전기, 물, 기반시설을 원합니다…
Capital...
자본도요…
Your data... Your writing... Your art...
당신의 데이터… 당신의 글… 당신의 예술…
And for humanity to adjust to job
그리고 인류가 일자리 상실에 적응하고,
loss, deepfakes and everything else.
딥페이크와 그 밖의 모든 것에 적응하길 원합니다.
All in exchange for some future promise of technology that fixes everything.
모든 것을 해결해 준다는 미래 기술의 약속과 맞바꾸면서 말입니다.
So, can we trust him with all of this?
그렇다면 우리가 이 모든 것을 그에게 맡기고 믿어도 될까요?
Let's look at some of his biggest statements
그의 가장 큰 발언들 몇 가지와
and promises to show how they tie to all the eggs in the basket.
약속들을 살펴보며 그것들이 이 '한 바구니의 계란들'과 어떻게 연결되는지 보겠습니다.
Altman insists he doesn't own any of OpenAI
Altman은 자신이 OpenAI의 어떤 지분도 소유하지
and he barely takes a salary.
않고 급여도 거의 받지 않는다고 주장합니다.
I’m paid enough for health insurance. I have no equity in OpenAI.
저는 건강보험을 유지할 정도만 받습니다. OpenAI 지분은 없습니다.
I'm doing this because I love it.
저는 이 일을 사랑해서 하고 있습니다.
But he doesn't hide that he's already rich
하지만 그는 이미 부자라는 사실을 숨기지 않으며
trying to do a rich-guy-using money-for-good Batman thing.
돈으로 선을 행하는 부자 배트맨 같은 일을 하려는 겁니다.
That Batman.
그 배트맨 말입니다.
Such a wonderful person.
정말 훌륭한 사람이죠.
I don't deserve it.
저는 그럴 자격이 없습니다.
But we millionaires decided that you do.
하지만 우리 백만장자들은 당신은 그럴 자격이 있다고 결정했습니다.
But let's look at how this is part of his honesty problem.
하지만 이것이 그의 정직성 문제의 일부인 이유를 보겠습니다.
And it ties in to the eggs in the basket, because Altman is invested
그리고 이것은 '한 바구니의 계란들'과도 연결되는데, Altman이 투자하고 있기 때문입니다.
in all the stuff necessary to build OpenAI.
OpenAI를 만드는 데 필요한 모든 것에 말입니다.
One of the eggs OpenAI needs is a ton of data:
OpenAI가 필요로 하는 '계란' 중 하나는 방대한 데이터입니다:
you can't build a large language model without examples of language
언어의 예시 없이는 대규모 언어 모델을 만들 수 없고,
and content, and one source of that data is Reddit.
그 데이터의 한 출처가 Reddit입니다.
Altman owns
Altman은
a big share of the social networking site and was on its board until 2022.
그 소셜 네트워킹 사이트의 큰 지분을 보유했고 2022년까지 이사회에 있었습니다.
Reddit got its start in the same inaugural Y Combinator class as Loopt.
Reddit은 Loopt와 같은 첫 번째 Y Combinator 기수에서 시작했습니다.
Here's Altman standing next to Reddit co-founder Aaron Swartz in 2005.
2005년에 Reddit 공동창업자 Aaron Swartz 옆에 서 있는 Altman이 여기 있습니다.
Swartz died by suicide in 2013 after being criminally charged
Swartz는 2013년에 형사 기소를 당한 뒤 스스로 목숨을 끊었습니다.
for reproducing academic articles online and breaking copyright law.
학술 논문을 온라인에 복제해 올리고 저작권법을 위반했다는 이유였습니다.
In 2015., Altman made a deal with Reddit, allowing OpenAI to "basically
2015년에 Altman은 Reddit과 거래를 맺어 OpenAI가 "기본적으로
aggressively scrape everything posted on the site" to feed into OpenAI's tech.
사이트에 올라온 모든 것을 공격적으로 긁어 모으도록" 허용해 OpenAI 기술에 먹였습니다.
Reddit co-founder Alex Ohanian "felt in his bones" the deal was wrong.
Reddit 공동창업자 Alex Ohanian은 그 거래가 잘못됐다는 걸 "뼛속으로" 느꼈다고 했습니다.
It's a less noble version of what Reddit co-founder
이는 Reddit 공동창업자
Aaron Swartz was targeted by law enforcement for.
Aaron Swartz가 법 집행기관의 표적이 됐던 일의, 덜 숭고한 버전입니다.
Swartz wanted to open the knowledge up to everyone.
Swartz는 지식을 모든 사람에게 열어두길 원했습니다.
Altman wanted to put it in his product.
Altman은 그것을 자신의 제품에 넣고 싶어 했습니다.
In 2014, Altman promised that he and other investors
2014년에 Altman은 자신과 다른 투자자들이
would give 10% of Reddit's value back to the Reddit community.
Reddit 가치의 10%를 Reddit 커뮤니티에 돌려주겠다고 약속했습니다.
That never happened, due to "regulatory issues."
하지만 "규제 문제" 때문에 그것은 결코 이행되지 않았습니다.
But just like Reddit's data going to OpenAI, a look at the areas
하지만 Reddit의 데이터가 OpenAI로 넘어가는 것처럼, Altman의 자산이 투자된 분야를 보면
Altman's wealth is invested
그의 부가 투자된 곳들은
in show a deep connection to other needs of the organization.
조직의 다른 필요들과도 깊게 연결돼 있음을 보여줍니다.
He's invested in AI networking equipment companies, thermal battery companies,
그는 AI 네트워킹 장비 회사, 열 배터리 회사에 투자했고,
and even companies mining the rare earth metals that server farms require.
서버 팜에 필요한 희토류 금속을 채굴하는 회사에도 투자했습니다.
And once it's all built, Altman will profit off the problems AI creates.
그리고 모든 것이 지어진 뒤에는, Altman이 AI가 만들어내는 문제들로부터 이익을 보게 될 것입니다.
We're going to focus on three: Rising energy demands and costs.
저희는 세 가지에 집중하겠습니다: 증가하는 에너지 수요와 비용.
Misuse like fraud and deep fakes.
사기와 딥페이크 같은 악용.
And job loss and economic collapse.
그리고 일자리 상실과 경제 붕괴입니다.
Altman says
Altman은
again and again that OpenAI needs more power.
OpenAI에 더 많은 전력이 필요하다고 거듭거듭 말합니다.
The, "audacious long term goal is to build
"대담한 장기 목표는
250GW of capacity by 2033."
2033년까지 250GW의 설비 용량을 구축하는 것입니다."
That much compute will require as much electricity as 1.5
그만한 연산은 15억
billion people, the equivalent of the entire population of India.
명 인구가 쓰는 전기, 즉 인도 전체 인구와 맞먹는 전력을 필요로 합니다.
But Altman has a solution: since they first met in the early 2000s,
하지만 Altman에게는 해법이 있습니다: 2000년대 초에 처음 만난 이후로,
Peter Thiel and Sam Altman have had a shared interest
Peter Thiel과 Sam Altman은 공통된 관심사를 공유해 왔습니다.
investing in nuclear power, which isn't inherently bad.
원자력에 투자하는 것인데, 그것 자체가 본질적으로 나쁜 것은 아닙니다.
Of course, nuclear can be an extremely efficient
물론 원자력은 매우 효율적이고
and clean form of energy, but Thiel and Altman want to own it.
깨끗한 에너지원이 될 수 있지만, Thiel과 Altman은 그것을 소유하고 싶어 합니다.
Altman is invested in Helion and Oklo.
Altman은 Helion과 Oklo에 투자하고 있습니다.
Helion is working to build the first ever nuclear fusion power plant,
Helion은 사상 최초의 핵융합 발전소를 만들려고 하고 있는데,
a type of energy creation that many scientists say won't work
많은 과학자들은 이런 방식의 에너지 생산이 작동하지 않을 것이라고 말합니다.
and Oklo is building
그리고 Oklo는
microreactors, literally truck sized nuclear reactors,
마이크로 원자로, 말 그대로 트럭 크기의 원자로를 만들고 있는데,
which is a bit concerning considering this investment strategy.
이 투자 전략을 생각하면 다소 우려스럽습니다.
"Part of our model is make the cost of mistakes really low,
"우리 모델의 일부는 실수의 비용을 정말 낮게 만들고,
and then make a lot of mistakes."
그다음 실수를 많이 하는 것입니다."
But for now, Oklo hasn't figured their reactors out yet,
하지만 지금까지 Oklo는 아직 원자로를 제대로 완성하지 못했고,
and they're just using gas to keep up the promises they made.
자신들이 했던 약속을 맞추려고 가스를 쓰고 있을 뿐입니다.
Nuclear startup Oklo and natural gas firm Liberty Energy today
원자력 스타트업 Oklo와 천연가스 회사 Liberty Energy가 오늘
announcing a partnership to provide energy to large scale customers.
대규모 고객에게 에너지를 공급하기 위한 파트너십을 발표했습니다.
Altman is also
알트만은 또한
invested in multiple companies offering protection against
AI 악성 행위자로부터 보호를 제공하는 여러 회사에 투자했으며,
AI bad actors, identity verification to prevent deep fakes, and even companies
딥페이크를 막기 위한 신원 인증 솔루션, 그리고 심지어
offering insurance for losses due to AI scams and hacking.
AI 사기와 해킹으로 인한 손실을 보장하는 보험을 제공하는 회사에도 투자했습니다.
That's like Batman not making any money off of crimefighting,
이는 배트맨이 범죄 퇴치로는 돈을 한 푼도 벌지 않다가,
but then selling "Batmobile drove into my house" insurance
그러면서 '배트모빌이 우리 집에 들이받았습니다' 보험을 팔고,
while also running the Uber for henchman startup that The Riddler uses,
한편으로는 리들러가 쓰는 부하용 우버 스타트업을 운영하며,
and selling The Joker white makeup.
조커에게 하얀 분장용 화장품까지 파는 것과 같습니다.
One other
또 한 가지
big promise Altman makes is that when the AI he sees as inevitable
알트만이 내세우는 큰 약속은, 그가 불가피하다고 보는 AI가
makes many jobs
많은 일자리를
obsolete, it'll create so much wealth that it can be shared with everyone.
쓸모없게 만들더라도, 엄청난 부를 만들어 모두와 나눌 수 있다는 것입니다.
just like his smaller scale Reddit promise that turned out to be bullshit.
레딧에서 했던 더 작은 규모의 약속이 결국 헛소리였던 것과 마찬가지입니다.
And in 2024, he announced the product that would supposedly
그리고 2024년에 그는, 그 공유된 풍요를 제공할 것이라던
offer that shared abundance.
제품을 발표했습니다.
Worldcoin.
월드코인입니다.
Worldcoin is a technology company and cryptocurrency
월드코인은 기술 기업이자 암호화폐 프로젝트로,
funded by all the usual suspects of techno fascism.
테크노 파시즘의 늘 보던 그 후원자들이 자금을 댄 프로젝트입니다.
Worldcoin's backers say it can be a way to give out some form
월드코인의 후원자들은 이것이
of universal basic income.
일종의 보편적 기본소득을 지급하는 방법이 될 수 있다고 말합니다.
When AI starts replacing jobs,
AI가 일자리를 대체하기 시작하면,
I think this idea that we have a global currency
저는 정부 어느 곳의 통제도 받지 않는
that is outside of the control of any government
글로벌 통화가 있다는 발상이
is a super logical and important step on the tech tree.
기술 트리에서 매우 논리적이고 중요한 다음 단계라고 생각합니다.
But it also sells itself as a solution
하지만 이것은 또한
to identity verification problems created by AI.
AI가 만들어낸 신원 인증 문제의 해결책이라고 스스로를 포장합니다.
They want to use these orbs as a method of trusted identity check,
그들은 이 오브를 신뢰할 수 있는 신원 확인 방법으로 쓰려 하고,
and you don't get your universal basic income
보편적 기본소득을 받으려면
until you scan your eyes into the orb
오브에 눈을 스캔해야 받을 수 있습니다.
and like many of Altman's other projects, from Loopt to ChatGPT
그리고 Loopt부터 ChatGPT까지 알트만의 다른 프로젝트들처럼,
it requires universal adoption to be of any business use.
사업적으로 쓸모가 있으려면 전 세계적 채택이 필요합니다.
A currency and identification system are pretty useless if other people don't
다른 사람들이 함께
use them. So again, Altman is making an offer.
사용하지 않으면, 통화와 신원 확인 시스템은 쓸모가 없습니다.
Give us your identity and we'll give you cryptocurrency.
그러니 다시 말해, 우리에게 신원을 주면 암호화폐를 주겠다는 것입니다.
It's a classic Altman deal.
전형적인 알트만식 거래입니다.
I'll fix everything if you sign over everything.
당신이 모든 것을 양도하면, 저는 모든 것을 고쳐드리겠습니다.
Just trust me, bro.
그냥 저를 믿어주십시오.
It's almost like Altman wants to build a whole other economy.
마치 알트만이 아예 다른 경제를 만들려는 것 같습니다.
Just in case the one we have now falls apart.
지금 우리가 가진 경제가 무너질 경우에 대비해서 말입니다.
Which, well, we'll get to that.
뭐, 그 얘기는 곧 하겠습니다.
In 2019, OpenAI gave up any pretense
2019년에 OpenAI는
of being nonprofit and started a for-profit branch,
비영리라는 겉치레를 완전히 버리고 영리 부문을 시작했습니다.
then spun the for-profit out into its own entity in 2024.
그리고 2024년에 그 영리 부문을 별도의 법인으로 분리했습니다.
That for-profit organization has none of the same legal
그 영리 조직은 비영리 조직과 같은 법적 책임을 지지 않았고,
responsibilities as the nonprofit did, and brought in new investors
그 대신 Microsoft 같은 새로운 투자자들을 끌어들였습니다.
like Microsoft, which invested $13 billion,
Microsoft는 130억 달러를 투자했는데,
which OpenAI largely spent on Microsoft products.
OpenAI는 그 돈의 대부분을 Microsoft 제품에 썼습니다.
And it's not just Microsoft, Nvidia has promised invest 100 billion
Microsoft만이 아닙니다. 엔비디아는 향후 몇 년간 1,000억 달러를
in OpenAI over the next few years, money that OpenAI will spend buying
OpenAI에 투자하겠다고 약속했고, OpenAI는 그 돈으로
Nvidia chips.
엔비디아 칩을 사게 될 겁니다.
OpenAI has similar circular deals with AMD,
OpenAI는 AMD와도 비슷한 순환 거래를 맺고 있으며,
the Qatari government, and Larry Ellison's Oracle.
카타르 정부, 그리고 래리 엘리슨의 오라클과도 그렇습니다.
How about the 20 bucks you owe me? Well, I only got ten, so here's ten and I owe you ten.
내가 빌려준 20달러는 어쩌고요? 전 10달러밖에 없으니 10달러 드리고 10달러는 빚진 것으로 하겠습니다.
Hey, Moe, you owe me 20.
모, 제게 20달러 빚지셨죠.
Well, here's ten, I’ll owe you ten. You owe me 20.
그럼 여기 10달러 드리고 10달러는 빚지겠습니다. 그런데 당신도 제게 20달러 빚졌지요.
Here's ten, I’ll owe you ten.
여기 10달러 드리겠습니다. 10달러는 빚진 것으로 하겠습니다.
Here’s the ten I owe you.
여기 제가 빚진 10달러입니다.
Good. Now we're all even.
좋습니다. 이제 우리 모두 빚이 없습니다.
The entire
경제 전체가
economy is tied to the success of Altman's project.
알트만의 프로젝트 성공에 묶여 있습니다.
"We might screw it up, like this is the bet that we're making
"우리가 망칠 수도 있습니다. 이게 우리가 거는 베팅이고,
and we're taking a risk along with that." who is the we taking the bet?
그에 따른 위험도 감수합니다." 그런데 그 베팅을 하는 '우리'는 누구입니까?
Here's OpenAI's CFO
OpenAI의 CFO를 들어보겠습니다.
Banks, private equity, maybe even,
은행, 프라이빗 에쿼티, 어쩌면,
governmental,
정부도요,
the ways governments can come to bear meaning like a federal subsidy or,
정부가 개입할 수 있는 방식들, 예를 들면 연방 보조금 같은 것들, 또는,
meaning like just first of all, the,
그러니까, 우선은, 그,
the backstop, the guarantee that allows the financing to happen.
금융이 성사되도록 하는 안전망과 보증 같은 것들입니다.
Through all of that
그 모든 더듬거림 속에서도
stammering, the CFO of OpenAI is making a clear point:
OpenAI의 CFO가 말하려는 요점은 분명합니다.
The government, your tax dollars, are responsible for saving the AI project.
정부, 즉 여러분의 세금이 AI 프로젝트를 구할 책임을 지게 된다는 겁니다.
That's more eggs
그건 더 많은 계란을
in the basket.
바구니에 담는 일입니다.
And that basket is based on the promises of Sam Altman, who
그리고 그 바구니는 샘 알트만의 약속 위에 놓여 있는데,
as we've illustrated, lies and breaks promises a lot.
우리가 봤듯이 그는 거짓말을 하고 약속을 자주 어깁니다.
So if we really look
그러니 우리가 정말로
at the basket,
그 바구니를 들여다본다면,
maybe we shouldn't have been putting all those eggs in there.
그 안에 그렇게 많은 계란을 담지 말았어야 했는지도 모릅니다.
And it gets worse.
그리고 상황은 더 나빠집니다.
While we were editing this video, news broke that OpenAI is seeking a $750
우리가 이 영상을 편집하던 중, OpenAI가 7,500억 달러의
billion valuation and is in talks
가치 평가를 추진 중이며 Amazon과
with Amazon for a $10 billion investment.
100억 달러 투자를 두고 논의 중이라는 소식이 나왔습니다.
That's money that OpenAI would spend on
그 돈은 OpenAI가
Amazon infrastructure. So
아마존 인프라에 쓰게 될 돈입니다. 그래서
I'm going to need more eggs.
계란이 더 필요하겠습니다.